<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Nova – Blog</title><link>https://akritbehera27.github.io/nova/blog/</link><description>Recent content in Blog on Nova</description><generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Thu, 24 Apr 2025 14:08:29 +0530</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://akritbehera27.github.io/nova/blog/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Why do our cheeks &amp; finger tips get pink in cold weather?</title><link>https://akritbehera27.github.io/nova/blog/why-do-our-cheeks-and-finger-tips-get-pink-in-cold-weather/</link><pubDate>Mon, 05 May 2025 11:49:05 +0530</pubDate><guid>https://akritbehera27.github.io/nova/blog/why-do-our-cheeks-and-finger-tips-get-pink-in-cold-weather/</guid><description>
&lt;p>&lt;img src="https://media.istockphoto.com/id/1455396963/vector/woman-wearing-warm-clothes-during-winter-blister-vector-cartoon-illustration.jpg?s=612x612&amp;amp;w=0&amp;amp;k=20&amp;amp;c=YcaIN6id3oGGmKiWzT6lpqbLX-Q9sOHLRX_Zj-QyAK4=" alt="" loading="lazy" />&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Our fingertips and cheeks often turn pink when it&amp;rsquo;s cold due to a process called &lt;strong>reactive vasodilation&lt;/strong>, which is part of how your body tries to maintain an appropriate temperature. This cycle of constriction and dilation continues as your body tries to balance keeping warm with protecting skin tissue from cold damage.&lt;/p>
&lt;ol>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>Initial vasoconstriction&lt;/strong>: When you&amp;rsquo;re exposed to cold, your blood vessels constrict (narrow) to minimize heat loss. This is why your skin might look pale at first.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>Reactive vasodilation (hunting response)&lt;/strong>: After a while, especially in extremities like fingers, toes, and cheeks, your body allows some blood to return to the surface in pulses. This is a protective mechanism to prevent frostbite by bringing oxygen and nutrients back to the tissue.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>Appearance of pink or red&lt;/strong>: The return of blood flow causes the skin to appear pink or flushed. In the cheeks, this is often more noticeable because the skin is thinner and has a rich blood supply.&lt;/li>
&lt;/ol>
&lt;h4>Why It Itches:&lt;span class="hx:absolute hx:-mt-20" id="why-it-itches">&lt;/span>
&lt;a href="#why-it-itches" class="subheading-anchor" aria-label="Permalink for this section">&lt;/a>&lt;/h4>&lt;ol>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>Nerve stimulation&lt;/strong>: When blood flow returns rapidly to cold, constricted blood vessels, it can irritate the surrounding nerves. These nerves may misinterpret the signal and produce an itching sensation instead of just pain or warmth.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>Histamine release&lt;/strong>: Cold exposure followed by rewarming can cause the body to release histamines—a chemical involved in immune responses. Histamine can cause blood vessels to dilate and trigger itching, similar to an allergic reaction.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>Skin response to temperature change&lt;/strong>: The sudden change from cold to warm can make skin cells behave abnormally for a short time, leading to temporary inflammation or irritation.&lt;/li>
&lt;/ol>
&lt;p>The itching you feel in your fingers or cheeks when they warm up after being cold is a result of &lt;strong>reperfusion&lt;/strong> ( the return of blood to areas that had reduced circulation ) . This is especially noticeable in areas with lots of nerve endings (like fingertips) or thinner skin (like cheeks).&lt;/p>
&lt;p>In more intense or chronic cases, this reaction can lead to &lt;strong>chilblains&lt;/strong> (painful, itchy swellings on the skin due to poor circulation and cold exposure).&lt;/p>
&lt;h4>Do you know ?&lt;span class="hx:absolute hx:-mt-20" id="do-you-know-">&lt;/span>
&lt;a href="#do-you-know-" class="subheading-anchor" aria-label="Permalink for this section">&lt;/a>&lt;/h4>&lt;ul>
&lt;li>
&lt;p>&lt;strong>The &amp;ldquo;Hunting Response&amp;rdquo;&lt;/strong>
Also called the &lt;strong>Lewis reaction&lt;/strong>,the cycle of &lt;strong>vasoconstriction&lt;/strong> and &lt;strong>vasodilation&lt;/strong> .It helps &lt;strong>prevent frostbite&lt;/strong> by ensuring intermittent blood flow despite cold exposure.&lt;/p>
&lt;/li>
&lt;li>
&lt;p>&lt;strong>Cold-Induced Urticaria&lt;/strong>
This is a condition where exposure to cold triggers &lt;strong>hives (itchy red welts)&lt;/strong>.
People with this condition can have allergic-like reactions just from holding something cold or stepping into cold air or water.&lt;/p>
&lt;/li>
&lt;li>
&lt;p>&lt;strong>Chilblains (Pernio)&lt;/strong>
These are &lt;strong>painful, itchy, red or purple swellings&lt;/strong> when skin is exposed to cold and rewarms too quickly. its common on fingers, toes, nose, and ears.&lt;/p>
&lt;/li>
&lt;li>
&lt;p>&lt;strong>Eskimo Nose and Ear Adaptation&lt;/strong>
People from cold climates, tend to have &lt;strong>shorter noses and ears&lt;/strong>, which are less prone to heat loss and frostbite—an example of &lt;strong>Allen’s Rule&lt;/strong>, which says animals in colder climates tend to have shorter appendages.&lt;/p>
&lt;/li>
&lt;li>
&lt;p>&lt;strong>Warm Sensation in Extreme Cold (Paradoxical Warmth)&lt;/strong>
In extreme cold exposure, people nearing hypothermia sometimes report &lt;strong>feeling warm&lt;/strong> before they lose consciousness. This is due to the failure of the body’s thermoregulation&lt;/p>
&lt;/li>
&lt;li>
&lt;p>&lt;strong>Cold Water Can Feel &amp;ldquo;Burning&amp;rdquo;&lt;/strong>
At very low temperatures, the skin&amp;rsquo;s pain receptors interpret extreme cold as a &lt;strong>burning sensation&lt;/strong>. That’s why frostbite can &lt;strong>feel like a burn&lt;/strong>, and can resemble a thermal burn.&lt;/p>
&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul></description></item><item><title>Can you change your Skin color ?</title><link>https://akritbehera27.github.io/nova/blog/can-you-change-your-skin-color-/</link><pubDate>Tue, 29 Apr 2025 09:01:54 +0530</pubDate><guid>https://akritbehera27.github.io/nova/blog/can-you-change-your-skin-color-/</guid><description>
&lt;p>&lt;img src="https://media.istockphoto.com/id/1884368685/vector/applause3.jpg?s=612x612&amp;amp;w=0&amp;amp;k=20&amp;amp;c=-2lEQ05qn95bET77_KHObxd7nV-TqFX0mBbrlNLHQpM=" alt="" loading="lazy" />&lt;/p>
&lt;p>A person&amp;rsquo;s skin color is primarily determined by the amount and type of &lt;strong>melanin&lt;/strong>, a pigment produced by specialized cells called &lt;strong>melanocytes&lt;/strong> in the skin. Here are the key factors that influence skin darkness:&lt;/p>
&lt;ol>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>Genetics (Inherited Traits)&lt;/strong>&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>Melanin Types&lt;/strong>&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>Sun Exposure (UV Radiation)&lt;/strong>&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>Hormonal Influences&lt;/strong>&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>Environmental &amp;amp; Lifestyle Factors&lt;/strong>&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>Evolutionary Adaptation&lt;/strong>&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>Medical Conditions&lt;/strong>&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>Age&lt;/strong>&lt;/li>
&lt;/ol>
&lt;p>skin color results from &lt;strong>genetics, melanin production, and environmental adaptations&lt;/strong>. It’s a natural protective trait that evolved to balance &lt;strong>sun protection&lt;/strong> and &lt;strong>vitamin synthesis&lt;/strong>. Variations occur due to ancestry, sun exposure, and health factors.&lt;/p>
&lt;blockquote>
&lt;p>There you can not change the &lt;em>&lt;strong>base color&lt;/strong>&lt;/em> of your skin
but you can get the base color of your skin by removing the &lt;em>&lt;strong>tan&lt;/strong>&lt;/em>&lt;/p>
&lt;/blockquote>
&lt;h3>Tanning&lt;span class="hx:absolute hx:-mt-20" id="tanning">&lt;/span>
&lt;a href="#tanning" class="subheading-anchor" aria-label="Permalink for this section">&lt;/a>&lt;/h3>&lt;p>Tanning is the process where the skin darkens in response to &lt;strong>ultraviolet (UV) radiation&lt;/strong>&lt;/p>
&lt;h6>&lt;strong>The Tanning Process&lt;/strong>&lt;span class="hx:absolute hx:-mt-20" id="the-tanning-process">&lt;/span>
&lt;a href="#the-tanning-process" class="subheading-anchor" aria-label="Permalink for this section">&lt;/a>&lt;/h6>&lt;ol>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>UV Exposure&lt;/strong> (mostly UVA &amp;amp; UVB) penetrates the skin.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>DNA Damage Alert&lt;/strong>: UV rays cause minor DNA damage in skin cells, triggering a repair response.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>Melanin Production Boost&lt;/strong>: this gives us the darker shade of our skin&lt;/li>
&lt;/ol>
&lt;blockquote>
&lt;p>Tanning does not happen to every one at the same rate it depends on the persons biological and environmental factors which influence there melanin production&lt;/p>
&lt;/blockquote>
&lt;h5>How long does a tan lasts:&lt;span class="hx:absolute hx:-mt-20" id="how-long-does-a-tan-lasts">&lt;/span>
&lt;a href="#how-long-does-a-tan-lasts" class="subheading-anchor" aria-label="Permalink for this section">&lt;/a>&lt;/h5>&lt;p>A tan from sun exposure typically lasts around &lt;strong>7 to 10 days&lt;/strong> before your skin starts to naturally exfoliate and regenerate However, this can vary depending on several factors: such as the time spent on sunlight , skin type and skin care routine&lt;/p>
&lt;h6>&lt;strong>Why Tans Fade:&lt;/strong>&lt;span class="hx:absolute hx:-mt-20" id="why-tans-fade">&lt;/span>
&lt;a href="#why-tans-fade" class="subheading-anchor" aria-label="Permalink for this section">&lt;/a>&lt;/h6>&lt;ul>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>Natural Exfoliation:&lt;/strong> Your skin is constantly shedding dead skin cells this process typically occurs every 28-40 days.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>Melanin Production Decreases:&lt;/strong> Once you&amp;rsquo;re no longer exposed to significant UV radiation, your body&amp;rsquo;s production of melanin (the pigment that causes tanning) slows down.&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;h5>How can you speed up this process:&lt;span class="hx:absolute hx:-mt-20" id="how-can-you-speed-up-this-process">&lt;/span>
&lt;a href="#how-can-you-speed-up-this-process" class="subheading-anchor" aria-label="Permalink for this section">&lt;/a>&lt;/h5>&lt;p>while the shading of tan is an natural process but you can fasten it up by:&lt;/p>
&lt;ol>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>Gentle scrubbing&lt;/strong>&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>Topical Remedies&lt;/strong>&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>Tan removal lotions&lt;/strong>&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>Using a Sunscreen&lt;/strong>&lt;/li>
&lt;/ol></description></item><item><title>Human History and Skin color</title><link>https://akritbehera27.github.io/nova/blog/human-history-and-skin-color/</link><pubDate>Mon, 28 Apr 2025 13:29:40 +0530</pubDate><guid>https://akritbehera27.github.io/nova/blog/human-history-and-skin-color/</guid><description>
&lt;p>&lt;img src="https://akritbehera27.github.io/nova/images/Pasted%20image%2020250428152655.png" alt="" loading="lazy" />&lt;/p>
&lt;p>A person&amp;rsquo;s skin color is primarily determined by the amount and type of &lt;strong>melanin&lt;/strong>, a pigment produced by specialized cells called &lt;strong>melanocytes&lt;/strong> in the skin .When ultraviolet (UV) sunlight hits our skin, people react differently based on their skin color, which is shaped by &lt;strong>biology&lt;/strong> and &lt;strong>evolution&lt;/strong>. The key factor is &lt;strong>melanin&lt;/strong>, the pigment produced by skin cells called melanocytes. There are two forms of melanin: &lt;strong>eumelanin&lt;/strong> (causing brown to black tones) and &lt;strong>pheomelanin&lt;/strong> (causing reddish tones).&lt;/p>
&lt;h4>Evolution&lt;span class="hx:absolute hx:-mt-20" id="evolution">&lt;/span>
&lt;a href="#evolution" class="subheading-anchor" aria-label="Permalink for this section">&lt;/a>&lt;/h4>&lt;p>We humans poped in the sunny savanas of africa where sunlight saturated the grounds, the sunlight mainly composed of Electromagnetic readiation and and other componets&lt;/p>
&lt;h4>Sun light&lt;span class="hx:absolute hx:-mt-20" id="sun-light">&lt;/span>
&lt;a href="#sun-light" class="subheading-anchor" aria-label="Permalink for this section">&lt;/a>&lt;/h4>&lt;p>&lt;strong>1. Electromagnetic Radiation (Primary Components)&lt;/strong>
Sunlight spans a broad range of wavelengths, categorized as:&lt;/p>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>A. Visible Light (38–49% of sunlight reaching Earth)&lt;/strong>&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>B. Infrared (IR) Radiation (~52–55%)&lt;/strong>&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>C. Ultraviolet (UV) Radiation (~7–10%)&lt;/strong>&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;h5>&lt;strong>2. Other Components (Minor but Significant)&lt;/strong>&lt;span class="hx:absolute hx:-mt-20" id="2-other-components-minor-but-significant">&lt;/span>
&lt;a href="#2-other-components-minor-but-significant" class="subheading-anchor" aria-label="Permalink for this section">&lt;/a>&lt;/h5>&lt;ul>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>Radio Waves &amp;amp; Microwaves&lt;/strong>&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>X-rays &amp;amp; Gamma Rays&lt;/strong>&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>Solar Particles (Solar Wind)&lt;/strong>&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;h5>&lt;strong>3. What Happens When Sunlight Reaches Earth?&lt;/strong>&lt;span class="hx:absolute hx:-mt-20" id="3-what-happens-when-sunlight-reaches-earth">&lt;/span>
&lt;a href="#3-what-happens-when-sunlight-reaches-earth" class="subheading-anchor" aria-label="Permalink for this section">&lt;/a>&lt;/h5>&lt;ul>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>Atmospheric Filtering&lt;/strong>: Ozone layer absorbs &lt;strong>most UVC &amp;amp; some UVB&lt;/strong> Water vapor &amp;amp; CO₂ absorb some &lt;strong>infrared&lt;/strong>.cattering (Rayleigh scattering) makes the sky appear blue.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>What Reaches the Surface&lt;/strong> &lt;strong>~50% visible light&lt;/strong> , &lt;strong>~45% infrared (heat)&lt;/strong> , &lt;strong>~5% UV (mostly UVA, little UVB)&lt;/strong>&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;blockquote>
&lt;p>&lt;strong>UV radiation triggers melanin production (tanning/darkening).&lt;/strong>&lt;/p>
&lt;/blockquote>
&lt;h3>Migration of humans&lt;span class="hx:absolute hx:-mt-20" id="migration-of-humans">&lt;/span>
&lt;a href="#migration-of-humans" class="subheading-anchor" aria-label="Permalink for this section">&lt;/a>&lt;/h3>&lt;p>The first humans, who evolved in Africa, had &lt;strong>dark skin&lt;/strong> as a vital adaptation to protect against UV radiation. About &lt;strong>250,000 years ago&lt;/strong>, Homo sapiens emerged, with major migrations starting roughly &lt;strong>100,000 years later&lt;/strong>. Movement out of Africa happened in waves, with significant migrations beginning around &lt;strong>70,000 years ago&lt;/strong>. In Africa, darker skin with &lt;strong>high eumelanin&lt;/strong> levels evolved as a protection against UV damage and skin cancer (melanoma). Melanin acted like a &lt;strong>natural sunscreen&lt;/strong>, shielding cells from UV harm.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>During this time, a mutation in the &lt;strong>KITLG gene&lt;/strong> appeared in populations moving into the Middle East, influencing melanin production and leading to lighter skin shades. This mutation spread with humans migrating into Europe, Asia, and the Americas, but it did not appear in groups that stayed in Sub-Saharan Africa or migrated south into Australia or Indian peninsula.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Later, as humans moved farther north into areas with less sunlight, darker skin became a disadvantage because it blocked too much UV, &lt;strong>hindering vitamin D production&lt;/strong> with the population spread to &lt;strong>northern Europe&lt;/strong> and &lt;strong>northeastern Asia&lt;/strong>, further mutations occurred (in &lt;strong>SLC24A5, SLC45A2, MFSD12, OCA2, and MC1R genes&lt;/strong>), promoting lighter skin to better adapt to regions with less sunlight. Individuals with lighter skin, producing &lt;strong>less melanin&lt;/strong>, absorbed more UV and produced more vitamin D, giving them a survival advantage in northern climates. .By &lt;strong>10,000 years ago&lt;/strong>, humans had populated nearly every part of the Earth. Skin color evolved mostly due to &lt;strong>natural selection&lt;/strong> based on &lt;strong>latitude and sunlight exposure&lt;/strong>, with darker skin near the equator and lighter skin closer to the poles.&lt;/p></description></item></channel></rss>